<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://jay-sonawane.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://jay-sonawane.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-07-11T23:21:43+00:00</updated><id>https://jay-sonawane.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Academics homepage, Jay Sonawane</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Shortest Intern</title><link href="https://jay-sonawane.github.io/blog/2023/the_shortest_intern/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Shortest Intern"/><published>2023-10-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-10-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jay-sonawane.github.io/blog/2023/the_shortest_intern</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jay-sonawane.github.io/blog/2023/the_shortest_intern/"><![CDATA[<p>Albeit the title sounds like a story where it is the story of an intern of a short stature: no, this that tale.</p> <p>The summer of 2023 was an exciting time. The “academic comeback arc” concluded since I finished all my courses. Futher, in the 8th semester my time-table was to sleep for 4 hours at night, wake up at 4-5am, work till afternoon, clinch another slim sleep for 2-3 hours in the afternoon. Particularly, this sleep schedule was dictated by the then’s necessity to put on multiple simulations. The semptiernal grind came to justice on 24th April when I submitted my first conference abstract to SISPAD.</p> <p>Around that time, en email popped up to all students advertising about Ph.D. positions available at IISC Banglore. Latching onto the idea of exploring an emerging domain in semiconductors, I mailed and received a positive reply from the professor regarding an intern. I was happy to go to IISC, although my peers would appreciate coveted internships like MITACs and DAAD-WISE or any other foreign Univ intern more. Eventually I made in to Banglore, and seemed to like the weather coz it is not as sweaty as Mumbai.</p> <p>The internship started off weird right away- since it was not a corporate intern, there was no HR onboarding or any introduction. I was informed that I would be given a decent research topic that would be enough to get results in 2 months as I had experimental resarch experience. Suprizingly, almost everyone in the cohort of co-interns was completing their second year of undergrad. In the first meeting I was told to work on designing a specific experiment concerning memory devices. The mentor assigned to me seemed pretty irresponsive, as I was tossed between 2-3 people having different topics of interest for the remainder of two months.</p> <p>Ten days in, I had mostly reading papers, with no equipment training. We had our first intern-presentation meeting. Other interns presented some literature review they were asked to. Funny enough, the postdoc (let’s call him Mr. NPD, the “leader” of the cohort who we were supposed to report to) started asking the presenters questions on basic physics. Mr. NPD asked one of them the numerical value of the thermal energy of electrons at room temperature. With a condescending tone, that of a teacher we all had in our lives, he retorted. Most of these interns had not even done a basic device physics course. I started to pity Mr. NPD who seemed to take pride in knowing something seemingly more important than applying it. The setting was his grande dinner, where he hogged on curious amateurs to satisfy his ego appetite and enjoy the knowledge gap. Eventually I presented about the experiment I was told to look into. Since I had not designed an experiment like this before, I presented on whatever plan/ flow that I could gauge. My mentor questioned me, saying that I was to present a literature review. Further, Mr. NPD asked me how many papers did I read. That was the funniest question someone asked me in a while. It felt like a mulish, rebelious teacher was asking me how many hours did I study. Next, he asked what topic I wanted to work on. To that, I replied that I had already been tossed between 3 people and their topics, I am okay with any topic. Just to diss me, he said- “If you are okay with doing anything, you might also do image processing”. At that point the I wnated to burst into laughter and but I disspointing grimace instead. Mr. NPD tried anything and everything he could clutch on to make his day. I calmly replied, I am here to study devices and device physics, not image processing. Mr. NPD reverted back with some early teenage like remarks on the lines of you yourself said you are okay with anything. Haha! What a day that was.</p> <p>Sometime during the same week, the group meeting with the professor was scheduled. I finally understood the hierarchy and the condescending atmosphere—Ph.D. students stuttered through presentations, and the Mr. NPD’s hands shook nervously. The group dynamics were clearly tense and toxic. Looking at the dilapidated internship experience prospects, I dwelled in the dilemma of whether or not to go back. I called Shubham (my mentor at IITB) and told his what all happened. His honest reaction- he laughed. He had already warned me earlier, he chuckled and asked me to reconsider my decision of going to the internship. After discussing, making pro-cons table, reconsidering, contemplating, I decided to come back to Mumbai.</p> <p>I think I returned after 15 days to Mumbai. With a heart full of joy and new vigour, I continued my research with Shubham. Looking back, I think that decision was on of the most crucial decisions in the course of graduate applications which were 5 months away.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="formatting"/><category term="links"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[spring & fall, looking forward to life]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Accidental Intern</title><link href="https://jay-sonawane.github.io/blog/2023/the_accidental_intern/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Accidental Intern"/><published>2023-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jay-sonawane.github.io/blog/2023/the_accidental_intern</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jay-sonawane.github.io/blog/2023/the_accidental_intern/"><![CDATA[<p>Albeit the title sounds like a story where an underserved college undergrad bags the coveted internship “accidentally”: no, this is that tale.</p> <p>The summer of 2021 will be etched in my mind forever. It was the summer post-2nd year of my undergraduate term. The spring ‘21 semester was the inflection point of a series of bad academic standing for the first three semesters, despite being interested in core electrical engineering. Academics that had taken a death blow for 1.5 long years, finally surfaced, especially due to EE207 (electronic devices). I bagged a summer internship at Carnot Technologies, an agri-tech startup through the placement cell, around April ‘21. Little did I expect to get an intern through PT cell due to the dilapidated academic condition, but I had done many projects in the hope of clutching the straws to compensate for bad academics. I got into Carnot chiefly because of a research project I did in the third semester (iSURP) based on hyperspectral image processing. April ‘21 was probably the happiest time of my life, getting an intern without even expecting as well as having a comeback from the academic downfall.</p> <p>So the universe had some other plans, it seems (no, I am not a pantheist, but it feels a little comfortable to address the “doer” of all the seemingly random yet organized events as the universe and not some single entity). Soon, in the second week of May, everything I considered the solid rock foundation of my belief system collapsed. The rest of 2021 can be summarised as biting the bullets, fighting adversity, and finding the right “Belief System” to sustain the newborn optimistic nihilist in me.</p> <p>I kept preparing for the upcoming intern season, did my intern work, and did a research project. Later in July, at the end of the internship, I was offered placement/ future intern/ open doors at Carnot for good work. All the division heads were invited to my presentation. It was a good day. The summer after the second year is an excellent time to think about what you want to do. The semiconductor industry was something I could see myself working in eventually (I can still see it). I spent time learning about the industry and studying what I like.</p> <p>In July, I prepared a little for the upcoming season and core was the only domain that I wanted to apply to. Texas Instruments was the first firm for core students. There was a test for shortlisting students for interview. I remember giving all intern tests, academic exams in a dilapidated state of mind but was sure that I’d do good. Texas Instruments shortlist came and there was no name in it. It had total 6-7 profiles, with some students getting shortlisted in multiple. There were electrical minor students shortlisted too (although no one got selected eventually). Just the fact that I wasn’t even shortlisted was pretty heavy to digest. Stoicism consumed me enough to not pay heed to whatever was going on. Over the complete semester, I was shortlisted in 0 firms. It is actually a throw of a die in intern season, many people don’t get what they want. So everyone eventually applies everywhere and gets an intern usually. The fact is if you don’t apply, you are not going to get selected, for surely. I was adamant on interning in core so applied to only core profiles and wanted to go to Texas/ Qualcomm/ Samsung Semiconductor (PS: The only companies that take DD students as interns).</p> <p>My plan was to do research under a professor at IITB otherwise, since I had this hint that I would be wanting to go for grad school eventually. I was already doing in-semester research and focused on improving how the transcript would look 2 years down the lane. Thinking that my grades were too ugly to get selected for a Univ intern or industry intern through apping, I didn’t apply anywhere except AMD and Intel (got no reply; AMD replied after a year :D offering a full time position thinking I must have graduated). Post Samsung semiconductor that came in October, I didn’t open the internship blog. So summer project was the plan.</p> <p>Fast forward to April ‘22, when the best semester ended, I had recovered in academics in three semesters after a bad series of the first three semesters. I had this fomo that everyone else was going to do an internship, whereas I would be doing research. I contacted my second year intern mentor Yash, to ask if I could continue again at Carnot. After a brief call with him, I got to know he had left Carnot 6 months prior and was at Atomberg. He asked me to send my resume. I had an interview and was selected for a sensors/ embedded RnD role, around May 10.</p> <p>So, a second year iSURP project led to a second year intern, and second year intern led to a third-year intern (ended up working with Yash again, eventually!). No shortlist in third-year intern rendered me to give importance to the thought of going to a grad school. In the end, I ended up doing a core intern as well as research with professor, which was the exact thing I wanted to do a year back then.</p> <p>My colleagues at Atomberg were the best one could wish for. We used to make fun of someone being the favored intern and someone neglected. Towards the end of the internship, everyone’s mentor discussed about PPO with their mentees informally, except me. We joked that I was “The Accidental Intern”, hence I am not granted a privilege as others (the real reason was that the HR said no PPO for Dual Degree students).</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="formatting"/><category term="links"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[march & april, looking forward to life]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Belief Systems</title><link href="https://jay-sonawane.github.io/blog/2022/belief_systems/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Belief Systems"/><published>2022-05-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-05-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jay-sonawane.github.io/blog/2022/belief_systems</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jay-sonawane.github.io/blog/2022/belief_systems/"><![CDATA[<p>It is human nature to cling to beliefs and certain belief systems. These belief systems are supposed to safeguard people against adversity in life. But the real interesting part comes when something challenges this belief system, and then it collapses. There are two possible future pathways; either you cling to another belief system, or your belief in belief systems collapses. This is the road to nihilism (the belief in nothing). Imagine yourself in such a situation where you dwell in rumination and conclude that these protective structures are flawed; they are themselves not to be trusted. Here you fall into an abyss of chaos and genuine aporia: should I feel protected by something, or should I be willing to confront such challenges without feeling that I’m being protected.</p> <p>Somewhere I read that in certain philosophies, the solution to the problem of tragedy lies in the willingness to face them. In this process, you grow, and you might grow larger than all this chaos one day.</p> <p>In my opinion, expressing belief/disbelief in belief systems is paradoxical in itself since believing in nothing is a belief in itself. One may not engage in any belief system by reasoning that the collapse of the belief system might be more “soul damaging” than not believing in anything and accepting adversity in life. Certain philosophies like stoicism help/claim to help in misfortunes and how we can control their impact on us. Now, whether to stay protected or vulnerable, be dependent or independent, have faith in something else or yourself, dwell in a rabbit hole or fall into an abyss, is your call to make; the fact that tragedy isn’t controlled by us is sempiternal, yet how we react to this tragedy portrays how strong we are.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="formatting"/><category term="links"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[march & april, looking forward to life]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Displaying External Posts on Your al-folio Blog</title><link href="https://jay-sonawane.github.io/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Displaying External Posts on Your al-folio Blog"/><published>2022-04-23T23:20:09+00:00</published><updated>2022-04-23T23:20:09+00:00</updated><id>https://jay-sonawane.github.io/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jay-sonawane.github.io/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry></feed>